

# Milena Vásquez-Amézquita

Faculty of Psychology, Universidad El Bosque

[ (+57) 601-6489000 Ext. 1605 | ■mvasquezam@unbosque.edu.co | 100000-0001-7317-8430 | ■XgNEpfgAAAA | Milena-Vasquez-Amezquita | 💣 grupo-codec.netlify.app/author/milena-vasquez-amezquita/

I am a researcher primarily interested in the neurocognitive bases of human affect and sexuality.

#### About me\_

Psychologist, Master in Basic and Applied Neurosciences and PhD in Neurosciences. Active associate researcher within the group CODEC: Cognitive and Behavioural Sciences (classification A1 in MinCiencias). Associate Professor at the Laboratory of Experimental Psychology of the Faculty of Psychology at Universidad El Bosque. Postdoctoral stay at Universidad de la Costa with funding from MinCiencias. I have been director and co-director of successful research projects from an experimental methodology in cognitive-affective neuroscience with internal and external funding, and I currently directing the research hotbed **SexCog**: sexuality and affectivity from a neurocognitive perspective. I have 13 years of professional and university teaching experience, applied to the development and implementation of undergraduate and postgraduate higher education programmes related to the neurobiological and cognitive bases of human behaviour, and I have supervised undergraduate, masters and doctoral degree projects.



#### Skills

**Programming** R (Basic, data analysis and graph generation)

**Quantitative Research** Observational-correlational studies, Simple and Mixed general linear models

**Recording techniques** Eye tracking (mainly), other basic HRV, EEG

Software RStudio, Tobii Pro Lab, Qualtrics, Psychomorph, WebmorphR, Mendeley and Zotero

**Languages** English/Spanish (native)

#### Education

Universidad de Valencia

**Universidad de Valencia** 

Valencia, España PhD - Neurosciences 2018

Valencia, España

MASTER'S DEGREE IN BASIC AND APPLIED NEUROSCIENCES

Universidad Cátolica de Colombia

Bogotá, Colombia

Psychology

2007

### Research Experience

**Universidad El Bosque** 

Bogotá, Colombia

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR

Jan. 2020 - Present

Universidad de la Costa

Barranquilla, Colombia

VISITING PROFESSOR

Dec.2023 - Present

Universidad Internacional de Valencia

Valencia, España

COLLABORATING PROFESSOR

Oct.2023 - Present

### **Professional Experience**

For a full list, and a description of responsibilities, please check my academic CV.

#### **ONG RedPapaz**

EXTERNAL SCIENTIFIC CONSULTANT

#### **Protect Children**

INTERNATIONAL SCIENTIFIC CONSULTANT

Bogotá, Colombia Sep. - Oct. 2022 Helsink, Finlandia Jul. - Aug. 2021

### **Accomplishments**

For information on grants, scholarships, awards and prizes, please check my academic CV.

#### **Selected Publications**

7 h-index 19 g-index 7 i10-index 20 Publications 387 Citations

For a full list, please check the publications section on my academic CV.

- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongoméz, J. D., Salvador, A., & Seto, M. C. (2023). What can the eyes tell us about atypical sexual preferences as a function of sex and age? Linking eye movements with child-related chronophilias. *Forensic Sciences Research*, 8(1)1–11. https://doi.org/10.1093/fsr/owad009
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Salvador, A., & Leongómez, J. D. (2021). Existen diferencias en la ratio 2D:4D entre delincuentes sexuales y no sexuales, y hombres no delincuentes? Un estudio en una muestra colombiana. Interdisciplinaria. *Revista de Psicología y Ciencias Afines*, 39(1). https://doi.org/10.16888/interd.20 22.39.1.8
- Jones, B. C., DeBruine, L. M., Flake, J. K., Liuzza, M. T., Antfolk, J., Arinze, N. C., Ndukaihe, I. L. G., Bloxsom, N. G., Lewis, S. C., Foroni, F., Willis, M. L., Cubillas, C. P., Vadillo, M. A., Turiegano, E., Gilead, M., Simchon, A., Saribay, S. A., Owsley, N. C., Jang, C. ..., Vásquez-Amézquita, M., ..., Coles, N. A. (2021). To which world regions does the valence-dominance model of social perception apply? Nature Human Behaviour, 5(1) 159-169. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-020-01007-2
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongómez, J. D., Seto, M. C., Bonilla, F. M., Rodríguez-Padilla, A., & Salvador, A. (2018). No relation between digit ratio (2D:4D) and visual attention patterns to sexually preferred and non-preferred stimuli. *Personality and Individual Differences*, 120, 151–158. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2017.08.022
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongómez, J. D., Seto, M. C., Bonilla, M., Rodríguez-Padilla, A., & Salvador, A. (2019). Visual Attention Patterns Differ in Gynephilic and Androphilic Men and Women Depending on Age and Gender of Targets. *The Journal of Sex Research*, *56*(1), 85–101. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224499.2017.13 72353
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongómez, J. D., Seto, M. C., & Salvador, A. (2019). Differences in Visual Attention Patterns to Sexually Mature and Immature Stimuli Between Heterosexual Sexual Offenders, Nonsexual Offenders, and Nonoffending Men. *The Journal of Sex Research*, 56 (2), 213–228. https://doi.org/10.1080/0022 4499.2018.1511965

### **Postgraduate Supervision**

For a full list, including undergraduate supervision, please check my academic CV.

Sara Silva Gómez

MSc in Neuropsychology

Yenny Johanna Baron Londoño

MSc in Psychology

Universidad Internacional de Valencia, España 2022-2023

Universidad El Bosque, Colombia

2019 - 2020

### About me

Psychologist, Master in Basic and Applied Neurosciences and PhD in Neurosciences. Active associate researcher within the group CODEC: Cognitive and Behavioural Sciences (classification A1 in MinCiencias). Associate Professor at the Laboratory of Experimental Psychology of the Faculty of Psychology at Universidad El Bosque. Postdoctoral stay at Universidad de la Costa with funding from MinCiencias. I have been director and co-director of successful research projects from an experimental methodology in cognitive-affective neuroscience with internal and external funding, and I currently directing the research hotbed SexCog: sexuality and affectivity from a neurocognitive perspective. I have 13 years of professional and university teaching experience, applied to the development and implementation of undergraduate and postgraduate higher education programmes related to the neurobiological and cognitive bases of human behaviour, and I have supervised undergraduate, masters and doctoral degree projects.



### Skills\_

**Programming** R (Basic, data analysis and graph generation)

**Quantitative Research** Observational-correlational studies, Simple and Mixed general linear models

**Recording techniques** Eye tracking (mainly), other basic HRV, EEG

Software RStudio, Tobii Pro Lab, Qualtrics, Psychomorph, WebmorphR, Mendeley and Zotero

**Languages** English/Spanish (native)

#### Education

Universidad de Valencia Valencia, España

PhD - Neurosciences

Universidad de Valencia Valencia, España

MASTER'S DEGREE IN BASIC AND APPLIED NEUROSCIENCES

Universidad Cátolica de Colombia

PSYCHOLOGY

### Research Experience.

**Universidad El Bosque** Bogotá, Colombia ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR Jan. 2020 - Present

Universidad de la Costa

VISITING PROFESSOR

Dec.2023 - Present

Universidad Internacional de Valencia Valencia, España

COLLABORATING PROFESSOR Oct.2023 - Present

### Professional Experience

For a full list, and a description of responsibilities, please check my academic CV.

**ONG RedPapaz** 

EXTERNAL SCIENTIFIC CONSULTANT Sep. - Oct. 2022

**Protect Children** Helsink, Finlandia

INTERNATIONAL SCIENTIFIC CONSULTANT Jul. - Aug. 2021

## **Accomplishments**

For information on grants, scholarships, awards and prizes, please check my academic CV.

#### **Selected Publications**

*h*-index *q*-index i10-index **Publications** Citations For a full list, please check the publications section on my academic CV.

- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongoméz, J. D., Salvador, A., & Seto, M. C. (2023). What can the eyes tell us about atypical sexual preferences as a function of sex and age? Linking eye movements with child-related chronophilias. *Forensic Sciences Research*, 8(1)1–11. https://doi.org/10.1093/fsr/owad009
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Salvador, A., & Leongómez, J. D. (2021). Existen diferencias en la ratio 2D:4D entre delincuentes sexuales y no sexuales, y hombres no delincuentes? Un estudio en una muestra colombiana. Interdisciplinaria. *Revista de Psicología y Ciencias Afines*, 39(1). https://doi.org/10.16888/interd.20 22.39.1.8
- Jones, B. C., DeBruine, L. M., Flake, J. K., Liuzza, M. T., Antfolk, J., Arinze, N. C., Ndukaihe, I. L. G., Bloxsom, N. G., Lewis, S. C., Foroni, F., Willis, M. L., Cubillas, C. P., Vadillo, M. A., Turiegano, E., Gilead, M., Simchon, A., Saribay, S. A., Owsley, N. C., Jang, C. ..., Vásquez-Amézquita, M., ..., Coles, N. A. (2021). To which world regions does the valence–dominance model of social perception apply? Nature Human Behaviour, 5(1) 159-169. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-020-01007-2
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongómez, J. D., Seto, M. C., Bonilla, F. M., Rodríguez-Padilla, A., & Salvador, A. (2018). No relation between digit ratio (2D:4D) and visual attention patterns to sexually preferred and non-preferred stimuli. *Personality and Individual Differences*, 120, 151–158. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2017.08.022
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongómez, J. D., Seto, M. C., Bonilla, M., Rodríguez-Padilla, A., & Salvador, A. (2019). Visual Attention Patterns Differ in Gynephilic and Androphilic Men and Women Depending on Age and Gender of Targets. *The Journal of Sex Research*, *56*(1), 85–101. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224499.2017.13 72353
- **Vásquez-Amézquita, M.**, Leongómez, J. D., Seto, M. C., & Salvador, A. (2019). Differences in Visual Attention Patterns to Sexually Mature and Immature Stimuli Between Heterosexual Sexual Offenders, Nonsexual Offenders, and Nonoffending Men. *The Journal of Sex Research*, *56* (2), 213–228. https://doi.org/10.1080/0022 4499.2018.1511965

### **Postgraduate Supervision**

For a full list, including undergraduate supervision, please check my academic CV.

Sara Silva Gómez

MSc in Neuropsychology

Yenny Johanna Baron Londoño

MSc in Psychology

Universidad Internacional de Valencia, España

Universidad El Bosque, Colombia 2019 - 2020